Register of the Uncommon Knowledge Video Tapes
Hoover Institution Archives
- Individual Program Descriptions, 1996-2010 (Folder 1-60, 62-126, on shelf)
  - Series 400, 1999-2000
    - "Trading On Our Fears: The World Trade Organization" No. UK415, 2000 May 6 (Folder VHS, box 6; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 31; D3, box 51)
      Kevin Danaher, cofounder, Global Exchange; Melvyn Krauss, William J. Clayton, senior fellow, Hoover Institution; and Jerry Levine, chairman, Northern California Export Council. In November of 1999, tens of thousands of people took to the streets of Seattle to protest against the World Trade Organization (WTO). How does the WTO work and why did it raise such a response? Does the WTO threaten environmental laws, human rights, and national sovereignty or does it provide the best framework for ensuring that all nations benefit from international trade? Were the protests aimed at the WTO in particular or at the concept of free trade itself?
    - "A Tale of Two Chinas: The Future of Taiwan" No. UK416, 2000 May 13 (Folder VHS, box 6; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 31; D3, box 51)
      David Liu, director-general, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Taiwan; Michel Oksenberg, senior fellow, Hoover Institution, senior fellow, Asia/Pacific Research Center, Stanford University; and Henry Rowen, senior fellow, Hoover Institution and director, Asia/Pacific Research Center, Stanford University. What is the future of Taiwan? Deteriorating Taiwan-China relations could be the first foreign policy crisis for the next American president. What is the history of the Taiwan-China situation? Is Taiwan an independent state? If so, why does the United States not recognize Taiwan's sovereignty? How should the U.S. respond if tensions between Taiwan and China increase?
    - "Working Hard or Hardly Working" No. UK417, 2000 May 20 (Folder VHS, box 6; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 31; D3, box 51)
      Ken Jacobs, codirector, San Francisco Living Wage Coalition; Thomas McCurdy, senior fellow, Hoover Institution and professor, department of economics, Stanford University; and Bishop John C. Wester, auxiliary bishop, Archdiocese of San Francisco. Since 1995, more than forty city and county governments across the country have enacted living wage ordinances. What are living wage ordinances and how does the living wage differ from the minimum wage? Is a living wage ordinance the best way to help low-income families or are there more effective methods of helping those in need?
    - "No Nukes Is Good Nukes: Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons" No. UK418, 2000 July 1 (Folder VHS, box 6; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 31; D3, box 51)
      Sumit Ganguly, visiting fellow, Center for International Security and Cooperation (CISAC), Stanford University and professor, political science, Hunter College, City University of New York, New York; William Potter, director, Center for Nonproliferation Studies, Monterey Institute of International Studies; and Scott Sagan, codirector, Center for International Security and Cooperation (CISAC), Stanford University. For decades the United States, the former Soviet Union, China, Britain, and France were the world's only nuclear powers. But that is changing. When India and Pakistan conducted nuclear weapons tests in 1998, they demonstrated that they had both the ability and the will to build nuclear weapons. Is the United States doing enough to prevent the proliferation of nuclear weapons? Are we prepared for the very real possibility that nations such as North Korea and Iran may soon be able to build nuclear weapons?
    - "Sales of a Death Plan: The Death Penalty" No. UK419, 2000 July 8 (Folder VHS, box 6; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 31; D3, box 52)
      Sam Jordan, director, program to abolish the death penalty, Amnesty International, USA, and Kent Scheidegger, legal director, Criminal Justice Legal Foundation. Is America on the wrong side of the death penalty debate? The worldwide trend is against the death penalty: more than half the countries in the world have abolished it, including more than 30 nations since 1990. So why do we have a death penalty in America? Is it to deter people from committing murder? If so, does it work? Or is the death penalty fundamentally a matter of justice, of punishing appropriately those guilty of the worst crimes?
    - "The Economy's New Clothes: Milton Friedman on the New Economy" No. UK420, 2000 July 15 (Folder VHS, box 6; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 31; D3, box 52)
      Milton Friedman, senior research fellow, Hoover Institution and Nobel laureate in economics. Internet technologies are transforming the way we communicate and do business. But, are we, as some claim, in the midst of the "long boom," a new era of unparalleled prosperity driven by unprecedented technological change or are we merely enjoying a bull market that has yet to begin its inevitable correction? What does the current economic boom have in common with the "Roaring Twenties" and how can we avoid an economic contraction as severe as the great depression?
    - "Milton's Paradise Gained: Milton Friedman on the Federal Budget" No. UK421, 2000 July 22 (Folder VHS, box 6; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 31; D3, box 52)
      Milton Friedman, senior research fellow, Hoover Institution and Nobel laureate in economics. What the next president decides to do with the federal budget will impact the lives of each and every one of us. For example, what should the next president do with the current budget surplus, pay down the national debt, set aside money to strengthen social security, or cut taxes? Milton Friedman answers these questions as well as addresses how the next president should approach the issues of education, health care, and the future of social security.
    - "That '70's Show: The Meaning of the 1970s" No. UK422, 2000 July 29 (Folder VHS, box 7; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 31; D3, box 52)
      David Frum, senior fellow, Manhattan Institute and author, How We Got Here: The 70's: The Decade that Brought You Modern Life, and David Kennedy, Donald J. McLachlan professor of history, Stanford University. Some argue that all of the major cultural trends that we associate with modern America entered the mainstream in the 1970s. What was unique about the 1970s? Should we emphasize the impact of '70s over that of the '50s and '60s?
    - "This Old House: The U.S. House of Representatives" No. UK423, 2000 August 5 (Folder VHS, box 7; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 31; D3, box 52)
      Newt Gingrich, distinguished visiting fellow, Hoover Institution, former speaker, United States House of Representatives, and Nelson Polsby, director, Institute of Government Studies and professor of political science, University of California, Berkeley. The House of Representatives is a venerable institution, now more than 200 years old. Is the structure of the institution itself appropriate to the demands of our modern, rapidly changing democracy? What reforms did Newt Gingrich and the Republican Congress of 1994 make to the House? Were his reforms just partisan fix-it jobs or were they much-needed repairs for the long-term? Is it even possible to make long-term changes to the House?
    - "Primary Colors: The Presidential Primary System" No. UK424, 2000 August 12 (Folder VHS, box 7; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 31; D3, box 52)
      Newt Gingrich, distinguished visiting fellow, Hoover Institution, former speaker, United States House of Representatives; Shanto Iyengar, professor of communication and political science, Stanford University; and Nelson Polsby, director, Institute of Government Studies and professor of political science, University of California, Berkeley. In the 2000 presidential campaign, Gore and Bush locked up their nominations almost six months before their parties' conventions. The Democratic and Republican national conventions, formerly full of high-stakes drama as the party delegates chose their presidential tickets, are now little more than formalities. Is the presidential primary system in need of reform or is it working just fine? Does the front-loading of the primary season make it impossible for a dark horse candidate to build a campaign? Do the political parties have too much power in the process or not enough?
    - "The Wedding Zinger: The Definition of Marriage" No. UK425, 2000 August 19 (Folder VHS, box 7; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 31; D3, box 53)
      Mike German, general counsel, Log Cabin Republicans of California; Andy Pugno, chief of staff, California state senator Pete Knight; and Felicia Park Rogers, executive director, Children of Lesbians and Gays Everywhere (COLAGE). The traditional notion of marriage, that of a union between one man and one woman, goes back thousands of years in cultures from around the world. But at the beginning of the 21st century, a debate is building in this country over the definition of marriage, specifically over the issue of same sex marriage. Are two men, or two women, in a committed relationship entitled to the sanctions and legal benefits of marriage? What roles will popular sentiment and judicial activism have in the struggle to redefine marriage?
    - "From Whom the Bell Tolls: The Spanish Civil War" No. UK426, 2000 August 26 (Folder VHS, box 7; 1", on shelf; Betacam SP, box 31; D3, box 53)
      Christopher Hitchens, professor of liberal studies, New School for Social Research and contributing editor, Vanity Fair and The Nation, and Ronald Radosh, senior research associate, Institute for Communitarian Policy Studies, George Washington University and coauthor, Spain Betrayed: The Soviet Union and Spanish Civil War. In 1937, thousands of Americans from all walks of life volunteered to fight in a poorly equipped army overseas, with no support from their government. What was it about the Spanish Civil War that inspired such idealism and courage? And was the fight to defend the Spanish Republic against General Franco and the power of international fascism as pure and noble as it seemed to these Americans? We examine the role that Soviet aid and influence, under Stalin's direction, played in supporting or undermining the republican cause.
    - No. UK427. See No. UK316
    - No. UK428. See No. UK302
    - No. UK429. See No. UK306
    - No. UK430. See No. UK307
    - No. UK431. See No. UK319
    - No. UK432. See No. UK312
    - No. UK433. See No. UK315
    - No. UK434. See No. UK318
    - No. UK435. See No. UK317
    - No. UK436. See No. UK326
    - No. UK437. See No. UK310
    - No. UK438. See No. UK311
    - No. UK439. See No. UK324
  - Series 500, 2000-2001
    - "The Ravaged Century: The 20th Century in Review" No. UK501, 2000 March 28 (Folder VHS, box 7; Betacam SP, box 33; Digital Betacam, box 57)
      Robert Conquest, senior research fellow, Hoover Institution and author, Reflections of Europe on a Ravaged Century and Christopher Hitchens, professor of liberal studies, New School for Social Research, and contributing editor, Vanity Fair and The Nation. For much of the one hundred years just past, the forces of freedom and democracy found themselves at war with two books, Das Kapital, by Karl Marx, which, of course, gave rise to Communism, and Mein Kampf, by Adolph Hitler, which gave rise to Nazism. Nazism and communism, how is it that these two totalitarian ideologies gained such a hold on tens of millions of people? If you had to decide the matter as a historical question, which one, Nazism or communism, did more damage to the fabric of our civilization?
    - "Terms of Endowment: The National Endowment for the Arts" No. UK502, 2000 May 25 (Folder VHS, box 7; Betacam SP, box 33; Digital Betacam, box 57)
      Alonzo King, choreographer and artistic director, Lines Contemporary Ballet; John Kreidler, executive director of Cultural Initiative, Silicon Valley; and John Podhoretz, columnist, New York Post. In 1965, Congress established the National Endowment for the Arts, declaring that it was "necessary and appropriate" for the government to fund the arts. We examine the question of whether the NEA really is "necessary and appropriate." What are the consequences of government awarding money to individual artists? What role does the NEA play in arts education? In short, has the NEA been a success or not?
    - "Making the Grade: Charter Schools" No. UK503, 2000 June 26 (Folder VHS, box 7; Betacam SP, box 33; Digital Betacam, box 57)
      Lauren Dutton, vice president of development western region, Edison Schools; Luis Huerta, researcher, Policy Analysis for California Education (PACE); and Don Shalvey, chief executive officer, University Public Schools. Charter schools are public schools that are allowed to operate outside the normal education bureaucracy. Do charter schools work? We examine this growing movement and look at the evidence: do charter schools outperform normal public schools? If so, why? Who goes to charter schools? And what happens when for profit companies run charter schools?
    - "Corporate U: Corporate Funding of Academic Research" No. UK504, 2000 June 28 (Folder VHS, box 7; Betacam SP, box 33; Digital Betacam, box 57)
      Mildred Cho, senior research fellow, Center for Biomedical Ethics, Stanford University; Donald Dahlsten, associate dean of the College of Natural Resources, University of California, Berkeley; and Chris Scott, assistant vice chancellor for research, University of California, San Francisco. Spurred in part by a congressional act which allowed universities to patent the results of federally-funded research, corporate contributions to academic research programs grew from $850 million in 1985 to over $4 billion by the early 1990s. In return corporations receive licenses to the patents generated by that research. Do these new academic-corporate relationships threaten the traditional functions of our universities to educate and to serve the public good by bringing the fruits of research to the public sooner and more efficiently?
    - "Peeping Coms: Privacy on the Internet" No. UK505, 2000 June 28 (Folder VHS, box 7; Betacam SP, box 33; Digital Betacam, box 58)
      Glee Harrah Cady, vice president, global public policy, Privada, Inc.; Karen Coyle, activist, Computer Professionals for Social Responsibility; and Deborah Pierce, staff attorney for privacy and identity, The Electronic Frontier Foundation. Congress is considering legislation that establishes a legal right to internet privacy. Many feel, however, that the issue is already settled and that it is impossible to guarantee privacy on the net. How is our privacy compromised when we surf the web? How is the internet industry responding to demands for privacy? Can individuals protect their own privacy online or is government regulation needed?
    - "Colombian (White) Powder Keg: U.S. Aid to Colombia" No. UK506, 2000 August 17 (Folder VHS, box 7; Betacam SP, box 33; Digital Betacam, box 58)
      Paul Boeker, president, Institute of the Americas; Malthea Falco, president, Drug Strategies; and Doug Ose, United States House of Representatives (Republican, California). It is estimated that Colombia produces 90 percent of the cocaine and 65 percent of the heroin consumed in the United States. In July of 2000, with bipartisan support, President Clinton signed a $1.3 billion aid package for Colombia to help that country with its war on drugs. The package includes providing the Colombian army with military helicopters and U.S. military advisors. Will the aid package succeed in stemming the flow of drugs from Colombia, or will it entangle the United States in Colombia's bloody civil war? Will American soldiers lose their lives fighting the drug war on Colombia? Is this a necessary escalation of our own war on drugs or a bad idea?
    - "Whose Genes: Patenting the Human Gene" No. UK507, 2000 July 13 (Folder VHS, box 7; Betacam SP, box 33; Digital Betacam, box 58)
      John Barton, George E. Osborne professor of law, Stanford Law School; Hugh Rienhoff, founder and chief executive officer, DNA Sciences, Inc.; and Seth Shulman, author, Owning the Future. Over the past several years, biotechnology companies, in a race to find possible new drugs, have deluged the U.S. Patent Office with tens of thousands of requests for patents on pieces of human DNA. Are gene patents being granted inappropriately, before gene functions are fully understood? Are gene patents encouraging or hindering the progress of medicine and the development of new drugs? Some critics have a broader objection to gene patents, arguing that it is inappropriate to give a company the exclusive right to genetic material that is inside us all. Are gene patents, as they suggest, patents on life?
    - "A Crack in the Ice: The Legacy of the Reykjavik Summit" No. UK508, 2000 August 21 (Folder VHS, box 8; Betacam SP, box 33; Digital Betacam, box 58)
      Hendrik Hertzberg, senior editor, The New Yorker, and George Schultz, Thomas W. and Susan B. Ford distinguished fellow, Hoover Institution. In 1986, Ronald Reagan and Mikhail Gorbachev met in Reykjavik, Iceland, to discuss nuclear arms control. The American and Russian leaders negotiated boldly, pushing each other far past the limits of previous arms control agreements. Reagan and Gorbachev were soon close to an agreement to eliminate all nuclear weapons. The stopping point: Gorbachev insisted that America's Strategic Defense Initiative, "Star Wars" be scrapped. Reagan refused, and no agreement was reached. What is the legacy of the Reykjavik Summit? Was it a failure, a historic opportunity squandered? Or was it beginning of the end of the cold war?
    - "Turn Out the Lights, the Party's Over: Why Socialism Failed in the United States" No. UK509, 2000 August 17 (Folder VHS, box 8; Betacam SP, box 33; Digital Betacam, box 59)
      Martin Carnoy, professor of education and economics, Stanford University, and Seymour Martin Lipset, senior fellow, Hoover Institution and coauthor, It Didn't Happen Here: Why Socialism Failed in the United States. Why did socialism fail to become a major force in American society? Every major first world country has been governed by a socialist or social democratic party at some point in the past century except the United States. Does socialism's failure in the United States stem from strategic mistakes made by socialist leaders? Or has socialism always been fundamentally incompatible with American culture?
    - "Don't Stop Thinking About Tomorrow: The Clinton Legacy" No. UK510, 2000 August 21 (Folder VHS, box 8; Betacam SP, box 33; Digital Betacam, box 59)
      Hendrik Hertzberg, senior editor, The New Yorker, and Christopher Hitchens, professor of liberal studies, New School for Social Research, New York, and contributing editor, Vanity Fair and The Nation. What will be the legacy of William Jefferson Clinton? Will the Lewinski scandal and the impeachment define his presidency, or will people set those events aside and concentrate on his political achievements or lack thereof? How serious was Clinton's misconduct in office? Was his domestic economic and political agenda a success or a failure? And how should we rate the foreign policy record of the Clinton administration?
    - "Patent on the Fritz: Patenting the New Economy" No. UK511, 2000 July 13 (Folder VHS, box 8; Betacam SP, box 33; Digital Betacam, box 59)
      Margaret Jane Radin, William Benjamin Scott and Luna M. Scott professor of law, Stanford Law School; Seth Shulman, author, Owning the Future; and David Weitz, partner, Wilson Sonsini Goodrich and Rosati. Is our patent system failing the new information economy? Critics say that the way the patents are being granted on computer software and on internet business methods threatens to impede technology and commerce rather than encourage it. Can industry resolve intellectual property problems on its own? Should we overhaul the patent system or just the U.S. Patent Office?
    - "The Battle for Britain: Britain and the European Union" No. UK512, 2000 August 21 (Folder VHS, box 8; Betacam SP, box 33; Digital Betacam, box 59)
      Tony Baldry, member of parliament, House of Commons, Great Britain; Robert Conquest, senior research fellow, Hoover Institution, and author, Reflections on a Ravaged Century; and Christopher Hitchens, professor of liberal studies, New School for Social Research, New York, and contributing editor, Vanity Fair and The Nation. Should Britain continue on the path towards political and economic integration within the European Union? Many in Britain are skeptical of the benefits of political unification with continental Europe. What does Britain stand to gain or lose by ceding sovereignty to the European Union? Would Britain's interests be better served by strengthening its special relationship with the United States?
    - "How Greedy Is My Valley: Techno-libertarians in Silicon Valley" No. UK513, 2000 August 17 (Folder VHS, box 8; Betacam SP, box 33; Digital Betacam, box 60)
      Paulina Borsook, author, Cyberselfish; John McCaskey, cofounder, E.piphany, Inc.; and T. J. Rodgers, chief executive officer, Cypress Semiconductor. Why are so many in Silicon Valley, from the cubicles to the boardrooms, likely to be libertarians, or techno-libertarians, as some have called them? What do these techno- libertarians believe about the role of government and entrepreneurship? How will they use the massive wealth that's been created in Silicon Valley during the past several decades? Are they promoting the public welfare or shirking responsibility by not participating in the political process?
    - "Up in Arms Over the Second Amendment: The Meaning of the Second Amendment" No. UK514, 2000 October 3 (Folder VHS, box 8; Betacam SP, box 34; Digital Betacam, box 60)
      Jack Rakove, professor of history, Stanford University, and Eugene Volokh, professor of law, University of California, Los Angeles. Does the Second Amendment to the Constitution confer an individual right to bear arms or not? Why is there so much disagreement about the meaning of this amendment? What does the historical evidence tell us about the intentions of the framers of the Constitution in writing this amendment? To what extent does our interpretation of the Second Amendment effect efforts at gun control today?
    - "Elephants on Parade: Conservatism in Modern America" No. UK515, 2000 October 3 (Folder VHS, box 8; Betacam SP, box 34; Digital Betacam, box 60)
      David Kennedy, Donald J. McLachlan professor of history, Stanford University and Pulitzer prize winning author, Freedom From Fear: The American People in Depression and War and Sam Tanenhaus, author, Whittaker Chambers: A Biography. For the last half of the twentieth century, the conservative movement in the United States was defined by two prominent doctrines: first, containment of the Soviet Union and second, an effort to roll back the expansion of the federal government that began with the New Deal. With the first adversary out of existence, and the second in retreat, what does American conservatism stand for today? We look back to the roots of the conservative movement, its guiding principles, and its leading proponents, including William F. Buckley, Barry Goldwater, and Ronald Reagan. We look to the future of American conservatism: Will it remain a unified movement or will internal tensions break it apart?
    - "The Thin Blue Line: United Nations Peacekeeping" No. UK516, 2000 September 27 (Folder VHS, box 8; Betacam SP, box 34; Digital Betacam, box 60)